<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An edict or statute lately set foorth by the French King, concerning the prohibition and punishment of single and priuate combats Published there in the Parlament, Iune 27. 1609. And first printed at Poictiers by Iohn of Marness the Kings printer, 1609. with his Maiesties priuilege or licence. Newly translated out of French.</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1609-06-26</title>
            <author>France. Sovereign (1589-1610 : Henry IV)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02981</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13123</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103958</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839700</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839700</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4146</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02981)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4146)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1106:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An edict or statute lately set foorth by the French King, concerning the prohibition and punishment of single and priuate combats Published there in the Parlament, Iune 27. 1609. And first printed at Poictiers by Iohn of Marness the Kings printer, 1609. with his Maiesties priuilege or licence. Newly translated out of French.</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1609-06-26</title>
                  <author>France. Sovereign (1589-1610 : Henry IV)</author>
                  <author>Henry IV, King of France, 1553-1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Hall for Richard Boyle, and are to be sold at his shop in the Black-Friers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: Fountaine-Bleau, in Iune .. one thousand six hundred and nine.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dueling --  France --  Law and legislation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4146:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4146:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EDICT OR STATVTE lately ſet foorth by the <hi>French King,</hi> concerning the prohibition and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſingle and priuate Combats.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed there in the Parlament, June</hi> 27. 1609.</p>
            <p>And firſt printed at <hi>Poictiers</hi> by <hi>Iohn of Marneff</hi> the Kings Printer, 1609. with his Maieſties Priuilege or Licence.</p>
            <p>¶ Newly tranſlated out of French.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Hall</hi> for <hi>Richard Boyle,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in the <hi>Black-Friers.</hi> 1609.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="royal_ordinance">
            <pb facs="tcp:4146:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4146:2"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ENRY by the grace of God King of FRANCE and NAVARRE:</signed>
               <salute>To all his Subiects greeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The Kings our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours, and We, haue made diuers Ordinances &amp; Statutes for the reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and aboliſhing of the too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and familiar vſe of duels and ſingle combats in this our kingdome. Mooued, as moſt Chriſtian Kings, with our dutie, and the diſcharge of our conſciences towards God: and as louing and gentle Fathers, with the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſafety and welfare of all our Subiects: as likewiſe with the care We haue of the preſeruation of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne authoritie, greatly offended and endammaged by the diſordered and too much vnbridled licence of thoſe aforeſaid combats. To this end haue We, by our Edict, dated in Aprill the yeere of our Lord 1602. and made by the conſent and aduice of al the Princes of our blood, the Officers of our Crowne, and others of our Counſell which were then about Vs, declared all ſuch, as vnder a pretence of drawing ſatisfaction from any man for a pretended wrong, ſhall either challenge, or cauſe him to be challenged, guiltie of high treaſon, and withall ordained they ſhall bee puniſhed accordingly: as likewiſe ſuch as ſhall anſwer any ſuch challenge, or aſſiſt &amp; ſecond ſuch as doe. With expreſſe prohibitions
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4146:3"/> to all our Officers, of what place &amp; qualitie ſoeuer, not to diſpenſe with ſuch as are guilty of the paine preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by the lawes of our kingdome againſt the Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of intereſſed Maieſtie, or high treaſon, nor to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate the ſame vpon any conſideration. Hoping that the grieuouſneſſe and terrour of the ſaid paine will be a meanes to repreſſe the libertie and deteſtable cuſtome of thoſe aforeſaid combats. But ſo farre are We from obtaining what Wee ſo laudably deſire, that, to our great griefe, and the no leſſe contempt of Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements and our owne, theſe ſingle duels or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats haue ſince beene farre more frequent then before. Which we haue obſerued principally to proceed from a falſe, erroneous and long conceiued opinion, too deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie rooted in the hearts of our Nobilitie, who haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies had their honour in greater eſtimation then their liues, That they ought not to dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or ſeek for any ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of receiued wrongs, but only by armes, without diſparaging their reputation, and incurring ſome note of cowardly baſeneſſe, but ſpecially in thoſe caſes, which they imagine cannot bee ſufficiently repaired but by armes. Notwithſtanding that We, to free them from this ſcruple and pretext, haue by our foreſaid Edict beene willing to charge our ſelues with whatſoeuer might bee obiected in this regard againſt thoſe that ſhould ſubmit and range themſelues to the obedience and obſeruance thereof. Moreouer, many as malicious as raſh, not well informed of what heauy cenſure and iudgement We do eſteeme ſuch actions worthy, doe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times on ſet purpoſe engage and precipitate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues thereinto, to the no leſſe endangering of their ſoules, then of their bodies, thinking to increaſe heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their reputation, and to get the ſtart and aduantage
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4146:3"/> of others. Howbeit, in effect they bee directly contrarie to true and ſolid honour, no way beſeeming a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and altogether diſpleaſing vnto Vs. So that from Vs they are to hope heereby for ſo little fauor, that We deteſt the vſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as We do thoſe that practiſe them, as a more then brutiſh madneſſe. Being willing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now laſtly to make cleere and manifeſt the falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of thoſe that build ſuch opinions vpon ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and deceitfull foundations; and by the ſame means prouide (as much as in Vs lieth) for the diſaſtrous incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences which are daily bred of the boundleſſe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow of this aboue ſaid libertie: as experience teacheth Vs, that ſometimes it is neceſſarie, for the better welfare of the Common-wealth, to alter and change the lawes, and to accommodate them to ſuch accidents as newlie happen, to make them the more profitable: Wee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe haue thought it requiſite, by the aduice of the ſaid Princes of our blood, Officers of our Crowne, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great and honourable perſons neere vnto vs, who by our expreſſe command haue often aſſembled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues together about this ſubiect, to adde to thoſe preceding Statutes and Decrees made by our Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, and by Vs, againſt the ſaid combats (without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoking or diſanulling them in any thing) this preſent Ordinance. Which We will and command to be kept, and inuiolably obſerued of all ſorts of perſons, of what eſtate or condition ſoeuer they be. Giuing them all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe prohibitions to this end: As likewiſe to the Queene our deare and beſt beloued Aſſociate, &amp; to all the ſaid Princes of our blood, other Princes, and to our principall and ſpeciall Officers &amp; Seruants, not to make any petition, requeſt, or ſupplication vnto vs contrarie heereunto, vpon paine of our diſpleaſure. Proteſting
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4146:4"/> and ſwearing by the liuing God, neuer to grant any grace or pardon, that may derogate from this preſent Ordinance, nor euer to diſpenſe with any man from the paines and puniſhments thereby preſcribed, in fauour or conſideration of any whoſoeuer, nor for any cauſe, pretenſes, or reſpects, that may be taken, propounded, and alleged, whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <label>I</label>Firſt of all, We enioine all our foreſaid Subiects, of what eſtate or condition ſoeuer they be, to liue heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in peace, vnity, and concord, without offending, wronging, contemning, or prouoking one another to hatred and enmitie, vpon paine of incurring our indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, &amp; ſuffring withall ſome exemplary puniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <label>II</label>Wee command that they honour and reſpect ſuch perſons as by birth, and by reaſon of thoſe offices and dignities wherewith our ſelfe haue furniſhed them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to be diſtinguiſhed from other, as We vnderſtand they are: and that ſuch as ſhall faile in this their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and reſpect, be puniſhed according to the qualitie of the perſon whom they haue offended.</p>
            <p>
               <label>III</label>The ſaid perſons of qualitie ſhall likewiſe abſtain from offending others, wherby to compell them to looſe the reſpect which is due vnto them. And where they ſhall ſo doe, ſhall be bound to ſatisfie as ſhall bee appointed.</p>
            <p>
               <label>IV</label>All differences that ſhall happen amongſt our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and whereof the examination and deciſion may and ought to be performed by iuſtice, ſhall be ended and voided by the ordinary courſes of law eſtabliſhed in our kingdome. And We forbid the parties to frame any
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4146:4"/> quarrell thereon, vpon paine to him that ſhall attempt it, of the vtter loſſe of the thing in queſtion, which now from this preſent we will adiudge to his aduerſe partie.</p>
            <p>
               <label>V</label>And foraſmuch as through the indiſcretion and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of ſome, others ſometimes endure ſuch grieuous outrages, that they thinke it impoſſible to draw any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends from them which may ſatisfie them in their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, but by way of armes; which being interdicted and forbidden by our ſaid Edicts, they either ſeeke it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or practiſe it by their friends, and exerciſe it dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, to the great contempt of our Lawes and our Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, from whence thoſe diſorders, and ſo frequent mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, which at this preſent wee will repreſſe, doe ariſe; Wee haue iudged it neceſſarie, for the preuenting of more perillous accidents, to permit, as by theſe preſents We permit all and euery perſon, that ſhall thinke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe offended by another in his honour and reputation, to complaine to Vs, or to our deare and beſt beloued coſins, the Conſtable and Marſhals of <hi>France,</hi> and to demand either of Vs, or them, the Combat; which ſhall be granted them by Vs, according as We ſhall thinke it expedient for their honour.</p>
            <p>
               <label>VI</label>Such as are in our Prouinces, may addreſſe themſelues to the Gouernours of them, and in their abſence, to our Lieutenants Generall; and in default of them, to the Gouernours or Lieutenants Generall of the Prouinces next adioining, to ſhew their grieuances to them, and to demand of them the ſaid Combat. Which Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours or Lieutenants Generall ſhall decide the ſaid dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, if it may be done. And if they bee of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that they cannot bee ended but by Combat, they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4146:5"/> ſhall giue vs notice of it, that they may receiue &amp; cauſe to be put in execution our commandement thereupon.</p>
            <p>
               <label>VII</label>The partie offending ſhall bee bound to appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Vs, or the ſaid Conſtable and Marſhals of <hi>France,</hi> as before the ſaid Gouernors or Lieutenants Generall in forme aboue ſaid, when hee ſhall bee called either by Vs or them, when our command or theirs ſhall haue beene ſignified either to himſelfe in perſon, or at his houſe two ſeuerall times, with the complaint of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie grieued: And the requeſt of the combat which hee ſhall haue made; whereto if hee be wanting, it ſhall bee then reiourned for three daies. And not appearing, he ſhall be ſuſpended for his diſobedience from his honor, be made vncapable of bearing any armes, and turned o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to the Iudges of our Courts of Parlament, euerie one according to his abode, to be puniſhed as refracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to our ordinances and decrees. Which Courts We enioine to doe their dutie heerein.</p>
            <p>
               <label>VIII</label>If one of the ſaid parties haue iuſt occaſion to refuſe the foreſaid Iudges, to whom they are appointed to preſent their complaints, hee ſhall haue recourſe to Vs, and We will ſee to it. But if the cauſes of ſuch refuſall be found light and friuolous, and vnworthy in ſome ſort to be accepted, hee ſhall be turned ouer with blame to the ſaid Iudges, who ſhall diſpoſe of it as they think beſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>IX</label>Hee that ſhall aske the combat, and bee iudged not receiueable, as hauing taken offenſe too lightly, and vpon ſmall occaſion, ſhall be ſent backe with ſhame.</p>
            <p>
               <label>X</label>The Attemptor that ſhall haue offred wrong vnto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4146:5"/> ſo as to preiudice his honour, ſhall be depriued for the ſpace of ſix yeeres, of all ſuch Charges, Honors, Titles, Offices, Dignities, &amp; Penſions, as he is poſſeſſed with, and not be reeſtabliſhed in them during the ſaid time, nor after, vnleſſe hee ſhall haue asked pardon of Vs, and ſatisfied the partie in ſuch manner as ſhall haue beene determined, and withal receiued from Vs new or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and declaration of our will for his reentring into the ſaid Charges.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XI</label>He that ſhall haue no Office, Charge, Dignity, or Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſhall loſe the third part of the annuall reuenue of all ſuch goods as he enioieth. Which thirds ſhall be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uied by way of preference to all charges, debts, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations whatſoeuer, and emploied to ſuch vſe as We ſhall afterwards declare. And hee whoſe ſaid thirds ſhall amount to leſſe then two hundred pounds, or that ſhall haue none at all, ſhall bee kept in priſon the ſpace of two whole yeeres, whereſoeuer We ſhall appoint.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XII</label>Whoſoeuer ſhall challenge any man the field in the behalfe of another, or certifie the challenge, or bee the bearer of any diſhonourable ſpeech, ſhall for euer bee degraded from his gentrie, depriued of armes, bee kept in perpetuall priſon, or be puniſhed with ſome infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous death, according as ſhall by Vs or by the foreſaid Iudges be ordained. Beſides, he ſhall forfet for euer the halfe of his goods, as well mooueable as immooueable.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XIII</label>He that eſteeming himſelfe offended, ſhall challenge the combat for himſelfe, not hauing formerly deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded leaue, as is heere enioined him, ſhall bee depriued from euer being able to make his party good by armes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4146:6"/> with any man, as likewiſe from obtaining any ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or amends for whatſoeuer iniurie he ſhall pretend to haue receiued. And if he that ſhall haue beene challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by him, ſhall giue Vs, or our foreſaid Coſins, the Conſtable and Marſhals of <hi>France,</hi> or at leaſt the ſaid Gouernours and our Lieutenants Generall, notice ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as We appoint the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to do, the Charge, Office, or Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which the ſaid challenger enioieth, ſhall be giuen, as from hencefoorth We ordaine, to the partie chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged, if hee bee a man of qualitie, and fit to hold the ſaid Charges: but if he that is challenged, repaire to the place appointed, or doth any thing tending to this end, without giuing notice as aforeſaid, hee ſhall vndergoe the ſame puniſhments with the partie challenging, and We wil then diſpoſe of the Charges, Offices, and Penſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of either partie as ſhall ſeeme beſt vnto Vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XIV</label>If contrarie to the prohibitions expreſſed in this our preſent Proclamation, it falleth out, that any fight, and kill another, he that ſhall haue killed, ſhall vndergoe the paine of death, declared by all our Ordinances. And till ſuch time as he be apprehended, he ſhall be depriued of thoſe Charges, Dignities, and Penſions, which are in his poſſeſſion. Moreouer, the halfe of the reuenue of all his goods ſhall for ten yeeres ſpace bee imploied to ſuch ends and purpoſes as We ſhall ordaine heereafter, without any ſatisfaction notwithſtanding to the heires of the partie that is ſlaine, becauſe he diſobeied this our preſent Edict. And if both the parties die in the ſaid combat, their bodies ſhall be depriued of buriall, and the thirds of their goods in fee ſimple bee emploied to that ſame end as ſhall bee ſaid. And if they haue no goods, their children ſhall bee declared ignobles, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4146:6"/> taxable for ten yeers. And in caſe they were before taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſhalbe proclaimed to be vnworthy of euer being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or holding any Charge, Dignity, or Office Royall.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XV</label>Such as ſhall haue aſſiſted the ſaid Combattants, if once they haue had weapons in hand, ſhall loſe both life and goods, according to our former Edicts. And if they haue beene but only lookers on, yet went thither to that end and purpoſe, they ſhall bee degraded from armes, and for euer be depriued of thoſe Charges, Dignities, &amp; Penſions, which they enioy. And if it hapned by chance that they were there, and neuertheleſſe did not indeuour to part the ſaid Combattants, and to hinder them from the deed, they ſhall be ſuſpended from the performance and poſſeſſion of the ſaid Charges, Offices, &amp; Penſions for ſix yeeres, and ſhall not after the ſaid terme of time be reſtored vnto them, till ſuch time as they haue asked pardon of Vs, and procured new decrees and orders from Vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XVI</label>Thoſe that of themſelues ſhall fight in ſingle combat, ſhall incurre the paine of death, or perpetuall impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with the loſſe of halfe their goods: and till ſuch time as they be apprehended, ſhall bee degraded from their Gentrie, and depriued, during their life, of all their goods.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XVII</label>If the offenſes be committed in places of reſpect, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the paines and penalties heere aboue mentioned, from which We proteſt neuer to exempt any man; ſuch as ſhall commit them, ſhall bee ſubiect to the ſharpeſt and ſeuereſt puniſhment contained in the lawes and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, as well ancient as moderne, of our kingdome.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:4146:7"/>
            <p>
               <label>XVIII</label>All Lawes, how good and holy ſoeuer, are neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe defectiue, and more hurtfull often times then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to the Common-wealth, as likewiſe not very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable to the Law-maker, vnleſſe they bee obſerued &amp; executed in euery point as they ought to be. Hence is it that We expreſly inioine &amp; command our ſaid coſins the Conſtable &amp; Marſhals of <hi>France,</hi> to whom the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and deciſion of theſe contentions, quarrels, and differences that concerne the honor &amp; reputation of our ſaid Subiects, appertaine, that they diligently ſee to the obſeruation of our preſent Edict, without vſing any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, or ſuffring it in any ſort to be counterchecked by any fauour or conniuence: Notwithſtanding all Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters priuate and patent, and all other Commands that may be receiued from Vs, which Wee forbid them to reſpect, as they deſire to be pleaſing and obedient heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vnto Vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XIX</label>We giue the like Commandement to all other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of our Crowne, euen in regard of thoſe that are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their charge; and to the Gouernours or Lieutenants Generall of our ſaid Prouinces, for our Subiects that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit in them, who ſhall repaire vnto them, as is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and ordained them by this our preſent Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: Reſeruing to our ſelues the liberty of adding heereunto by way of augmenting and enlarging the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, that which time, the practiſe and experience of ſuch orders as in it are expreſſed, ſhall teach Vs to bee neceſſarie, That We may cauſe the libertie and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion aboueſaid of theſe duels and ſingle combats, vtterly to ceaſe in this our kingdome, as things too raſhly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, and with preſumption on our authoritie; and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4146:7"/> by this meanes free our ſaid Subiects from the ineuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perils of their ſoules, as of their bodies and goods, into which they runne headlong continually by ſuch meanes: Which We haue declared, and by theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents doe declare, to be altogether infamous &amp; ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as repugnant to true honour, as thoſe, to which a paſſage by theſe Preſents is made them, ſhall from hencefoorth be both honorable and profitable to them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XX</label>And to the intent it may pleaſe God to bleſſe our preſent intention, and to direct and proſper it to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the ſafety of our ſaid Subiects, We haue vowed, allotted, and appointed all ſuch mony as ſhall ariſe from the pecuniary penalties, ſeiſures, perception, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying of the profits and reuenewes of ſuch as ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe this our ſaid Edict, to be imploied as well for the nouriſhing of the poore, and for the erecting of an Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall Royall, which Wee haue determined to build ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly to this end and purpoſe, as alſo for the repairing of decaied Churches in this our kingdome, not ſuffring the ſaid ſummes of mony to be diuerted from theſe vſes vpon paine of grieuous puniſhment.</p>
            <p>In the meane time We will and command, that the ſaid ſummes of money bee receiued by the Receiuer of Gods Hoſpitall in our good City of <hi>Paris,</hi> who ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently keepe it till ſuch time as We ſhall otherwiſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe of it. Wee alſo giue commandement to all our truſtie friends, the Iudges of our Courts of Parlament, Shiriffes, Bailiffes, and other our Iuſtices and Officers, to whom it appertaineth, That they cauſe the contents of theſe Preſents to be read, publiſhed, and enregiſtred, kept, and obſerued, and that themſelues keepe and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the ſame inuiolably, and without infringement:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4146:8"/> For ſuch is our pleaſure. And to the end it may remaine for euer firme and ſtable, Wee haue ſigned theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents with our owne hand, and cauſed our Seale to bee put thereto, without preiudice either to our own right, or that of other in any thing.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at <hi>Fountaine-Bleau,</hi> 
                  <date>in Iune, the yeere of grace one thouſand ſix hundred and nine; and of our raigne the twentieth.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Signed, HENRY.</signed> And a little lower, <signed>BRVLLART.</signed> And on the ſide, <signed>VISA.</signed> And ſealed with greene wax, on labels of red and greene ſilke.
</closer>
            <postscript>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:4146:8"/>
               <p>Read, publiſhed, and regiſtred, at the requeſt of the Kings Atturney Generall, without preiudice to any rights, or obligations of pretended Creditors. And or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that Copies compared with the originall ſhall be ſent to the Bayli-wickes, and Counties of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince to be read, publiſhed, and regiſtred. Enioynd the Subſtitutes of the Kings Atturney Generall to proceed in the publiſhing, and to certifie the Court of their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence within the month.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>At <hi>PARIS</hi> in Parlament, <date>26 Iune. 1609.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Signed DV-TILLET.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:4146:9"/>
            <p>THis required the Kings Atturney Generall, ordained that his Maieſties Edict now read, ſhould bee regiſtred in the Court Rolles, that recourſe might be had thereto when need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and to bee publiſhed with ſound of trumpet thorow all the ſtreets and corners of this City, where Proclamations are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to be made, and ſent with all diligence, at the charges of the Notarie, to euery particular Court, there to bee likewiſe read, publiſhed, and regiſtred; whereof the Officers ſhall certifie the Kings Atturney. It is enioined, and We enioine, all perſons of what eſtate and condition ſoeuer they bee, to obey it, vpon paine as aforeſaid.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Made <date>this 11. of Iuly, 1609.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <p>THis preſent Proclamation hath beene read and publiſhed the Court being aſſembled, and beſides thorow all the ſtreets of this Towne of <hi>Poictiers,</hi> by me <hi>Stenon Renier</hi> Sergeant Royall, hauing with mee <hi>Peter Pareau</hi> Crier, and Trumpetter ordinarie of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Made this 11. of Iuly, 1609.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Signed
<list>
                     <item>Renier and</item>
                     <item>Pareau.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4146:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
